Hi. This is Matt Baker. Today I'm going to show
you the family tree of Chinese emperors. I'll
mostly be focusing on the medieval and modern
dynasties but before we get to them I am going
to start with the legendary Yellow Emperor and
briefly summarize the dynasties of kings and
emperors who ruled China during ancient times. As
you can see, for most of the video, I'll be using
our brand new East Asian Royal Family Trees chart,
which is available as a poster from our website
UsefulCharts.com. In addition to China, it also
covers Japan (which I've already done a video on)
as well as Korea and Mongolia (which I'll be doing
videos on in the future). We also sell two charts
covering the many European royal family trees,
a Timeline of World History, as well as many
other titles so, again, if you’re interested
in learning more about any of these posters,
just head over to UsefulCharts.com or simply click
the link in the description or pinned comment.
Okay, the first thing you need to know
about China is that, unlike Japan,
it has been ruled by many different
dynasties instead of just one. In fact,
one of the most important concepts
in Chinese history is the idea of
the Mandate of Heaven—which basically states
that it's normal for one dynasty to overthrow
another because whenever that happens, it's
because the old dynasty had become corrupt and
therefore Heaven decided that a new dynasty was
needed, in order to restore peace and stability.
According to legend, Chinese history begins with
the three sovereigns: Fuxi and Nüwa, who created
humans and Shennong, who invented farming. They
are then followed by five legendary emperors,
the first of which, called the Yellow Emperor, is
considered to be the founder of China. However,
the first dynasty is considered to be the Xia
dynasty, which was founded by Yu the Great,
who—according to legend—was the first to control
the floods that occur along the Yellow River. But,
there is no firm evidence for the Xia dynasty’s
existence and therefore it too is considered to
be mostly legendary—meaning that Chinese
history really begins around 1600 BCE
with the Shang dynasty—the first set of
monarchs for which we have verifiable
records. But take note, the Shang rulers were not
emperors—they were kings. During their tenure,
bronze-working became common in China
and the earliest form of Chinese writing
developing (using the Chinese characters
that evolved into the ones still used today).
But then, in 1046, the Shang dynasty
was overthrown by the Zhou dynasty,
which can be divided into the initial Western Zhou
and the later Eastern Zhou. You see, in 771 BCE,
their capital was overthrown, forcing
them to set up a new capital in the East,
where they continued to reign, but mostly as
just figureheads, with feudal lords holding
most of the real power. This coincided with
what’s called the Spring & Autumn Period,
which is when the groundwork for Chinese
philosophy was laid, through figures such
as as Lao Tzu, and Confucious. We then get
the Warring States Period, which is when the
political situation got really chaotic and
the Zhou dynasty formally came to an end.
Which brings us to the actual first emperor
of China: Qin Shi Huang, who managed to
conquer and thus unite all of the Chinese states,
completing the process in 221 BCE. At this point,
he upgraded his title of “Wang” (meaning
king) to Huang-di (meaning supreme ruler,
or emperor). In addition to being the first
emperor, he is also remembered for starting
the construction of the Great Wall of
China and for being buried with an army
of 8,000 terracotta soldiers. But for all of his
accomplishments, his dynasty did not last long,
although the name of the dynasty did, because
it’s from the word Qin that we get the word China.
So, within a decade of the first emperor’s
death, a new dynasty took over: the Han dynasty,
founded by Emperor Gaozu. It would go on to
last for about 400 years and is considered to
be China’s first golden age. It’s most famous
ruler is Emperor Wu, who established the Silk
Road connecting China to India, the Middle
East, and Europe for the first time ever. His
descendants ruled until the short-lived Xin
dynasty, when a usurper briefly took over,
only to be followed by a restored Han dynasty,
sometimes called the Eastern Han dynasty,
which lasted until 220 CE. At this point we get
the three kingdoms period, a brief re-unification
under the Jin dynasty, and then a period
known as the Northern and Southern dynasties.
Which bring us to the top of the
East Asian Royal Family Trees poster,
which I’ll be using for the rest of the video.
After the Northern and Southern dynasties,
China was once again re-united by Emperor Wen
of the Sui dynasty. But, as you can see, the Sui
dynasty was short-lived, being quickly replaced
by the Tang dynasty, led by Emperor Gaozu. Now,
if you remember, the first emperor of the
earlier Han dynasty was also named Gaozu.
This is not a coincidence but rather the result
of the how Chinese emperors are named. You see,
each emperor actually has many different
names, such as their birth name, era name,
and temple name, among several others. During
their lifetimes, each emperor would simply have
been referred to as Huang-di but after death,
each one was given a special temple name to be
used for ceremonial purposes. In the case
of both Gaozu of Han and Gaozu of Tang,
they were both given the name “Gaozu” because
it literally means “highest ancestor”. So, take
note that, until we reach the Ming dynasty, all
emperors will be listed using their temple names.
Anyhow, Gaozu was followed by Taizong, who
was given that name because it means “great
ancestor”. What made Taizong so great
was that he was open to following the
advice of his advisors, which led China to
reach new levels of wealth and stability,
ushering in a second golden age. In
fact, during his reign, China’s capital
city (Chang'an) became the largest and most
prosperous city in the entire world and thus
most historians today consider Taizong to have
been the greatest Chinese emperor of all time.
He was followed by his son Gaozong, who
ended up falling in love with one of his
father’s lower ranking concubines named Wu
Zetian, eventually making her his official
Empress. He however had bad health and eventually
Wu Zetian took over as regent. After Gaozong died,
Wu Zetian continued to serve as regent
during the first reigns of both Zhongzong
and Ruizong. But then in 690, Wu Zetian made
herself emperor—becoming the first, and only,
female emperor in Chinese history. Thus, for
15 years, the Tang dynasty was replaced by
the Wu Zhou dynasty. But eventually, Wu
Zetian was deposed with both Zhongzong
and Ruizong once again serving as emperors (as
well as Zhongzong’s son Shang for just 17 days.
After all this back-and-forthing, the throne
finally settled on Ruizong’s son Xuanzong,
who had a nice long reign of 44 years—which is
when the Tang dynasty reached its peak. In fact,
he would have reigned even longer had
it not been for the An Lushan Rebellion,
which started when a general named An Lushan
tried to overthrow the Tang dynasty. During
the initial stages of the rebellion, An Lushan
managed to capture the capital city Chang'an,
forcing Emperor Xuanzong to flee. At this point,
Xuanzong’s son Suzong declared himself to be
emperor. Suzong managed to retake the capital
but the rebellion wasn’t fully quashed until
the first year of his son Daizong’s reign. By
the end, at least 13 million lives were lost,
making it the deadliest uninterrupted war in human
history, relative to the global population at the
time. As you can imagine, this put an end to the
Tang dynasty’s golden age and from here onwards,
while the dynasty did continue, it was definitely
in decline. The final blow came due to another
rebellion, the Huang Chao Rebellion, which
occurred during the reign of Xizong. This left
China in complete disarray, resulting in the
ultimate collapse of the Tang dynasty in 907.
What followed was the Five Dynasties
and Ten Kingdoms Period during which
time China fractured into a bunch of small
states. But then, as we’ve seen before,
re-unification was once again achieved, this
time by the Song Dynasty, initially led by
Taizu and then by Taizu’s brother Taizong. The
line continued through Taizong with his grandson
Renzong becoming the longest-reigning Song
emperor at 41 years. Now, the most important
thing to note about the Song dynasty period is its
technological achievements, four in particular,
all of which were major improvements on the
four great inventions of ancient China. The
first was paper currency. While paper itself
was invented during the Han period and paper
notes were sometimes used during the Tang period,
it wasn’t until the Song era that the government
starting issuing official paper currency. The
second achievement was a better compass. Again,
the original compass was invented during the Han
period but those were quite heavy and therefore
not really used for navigation. However, during
the Song era, portable compasses were invented,
meaning that you could take one on a boat
or any long journey. Third, was gunpowder.
Gunpowder was first formulated during the Tang
period but it wasn’t until the Song era that it
was used for military purposes. Finally, there was
movable type printing. While whole-page woodblock
printing had been used previously, during the
Song era, ceramic tiles for each letter were
created so that you could move them around and
re-use them to print whatever text you wanted.
Now, one of the most interesting emperors
of the Song dynasty is Huizong. He was a
man of the arts—a truly great painter,
poet, and calligrapher—but tragically,
this meant that he didn’t pay enough attention to
politics and what happened was that a people group
to the north (known as the Jurchens) were allowed
to become really powerful. Led by Taizu of Jin,
they founded the state of Great Jin, which
eventually attacked Song China. Realizing his
mistake, Huizong abdicated, passing the throne to
his reluctant son Qinzong. But, within a month,
the Great Jin was able to depose Qinzong
and conquer all of Northern China. However,
Qinzong’s brother, Gaozong, was able to flee
south and set up a new capital there. Thus,
the Song dynasty was able to continue, but only
in the southern half of the empire. This is why,
from this point forward, they are labelled as
the Southern Song. Gaozong’s only biological son,
Zhao Fu, died at age 2, and thus after
Gaozong’s death, the line passed to
the descendants of the Song dynasty’s founder,
Taizu, first this branch, and then this branch.
Now, during the Southern Song period, an even
greater power to the north arose—in fact,
one of the greatest that the world has ever
seen: the Mongols, led by Genghis Khan. While
he himself wasn’t able to conquer China during
his lifetime, the Jin Dynasty ended up falling
to his son Ögedei Khan; and the Southern Song to
his grandson Kublai Khan. It was during this time
period that Marco Polo famously visited China. In
1279, Khan became the undisputed Emperor of China,
and from here onwards he and descendants are
known as the Yuan dynasty of China. After death,
Kublai Khan received the temple name Shizu, with
the next emperor being his grandson Chengzong.
But then, after Chengzong, things bounced
back forth between various branches of the
tree before finally settling on Huizong, who had
a nice long reign of 35 years. However, in 1368,
after 89 years of Mongol-rule, China won back its
independence with the rise of the Ming dynasty,
initially led by the Hongwu Emperor. At
this point, the Yuan dynasty did continue
but only to the north of China, which is why
we get a label change here to Northern Yuan.
Now, before I continue, I want to point out
that UsefulCharts currently has a campaign
over on Kickstarter, where we have launched
our expanded tree of life project Of the many
educational posters that we sell at UsefulCharts,
one of the most popular has always been our
Evolutionary Tree of Life chart, which we did
a major update of in 2024. Ever since then,
I’ve been wanting to go into certain parts of that
tree in greater detail—which is what this project
is all about. Basically, the goal is to create a
series of 4 posters, each of which will expand on
a different part of the tree of life. The first
one, Plants & Fungi, is already finished but in
order to complete the other three, we need your
help. The exact breakdown is yet to be determined,
but they are likely to be: Insects & Other
Invertebrates; Fish, Amphibians, and Reptiles;
and finally Bird & Mammals. Each chart will be
printed on thick, quality paper at an amazingly
high resolution so if you want be among
the first to receive one of these titles,
I encourage you to pre-order now. You can choose
to receive any one chart out of the four, any
two charts out of the four, or the full set. You
can also simply show your support by pledging $1,
which helps drive the Kickstarter algorithm.
We’ve got some fun stretch goals planned and
will have everything printed and mailed out by
the end of November, so whether you’re buying
for yourself or giving them as holiday gifts,
I encourage you to back the project right now.
Okay, let’s now take a look at the Ming
dynasty. First off, as I mentioned earlier,
from here onwards, era names will be used for
emperors instead of temple names (as this is the
convention used by most historians). Second,
take note that it was during the Ming period
that Beijing as we know it today started to be
built, on top of what had previously been the
Yuan capital. This included famous structures
such as the Forbidden City, Tiananmen gate, and
Temple of Heaven—all of which were commissioned
by the Yongle emperor, who is considered to have
been the greatest emperor of the Ming dynasty.
You see, it was he who named Beijing “bei jing”,
which literally just means “Northern capital”. The
Yongle emperor is also the one who commissioned
the great explorer Zheng He, whose famous treasure
fleet travelled all over Southeast Asia, India,
and the Middle East—even going as far
as what is today Kenya, in East Africa.
The other thing that comes to mind when people
think about the Ming dynasty is china. Not the
country itself but the type of ceramic known as
porcelain or “fine china” (which was obviously
named after the country). You see, during
the reign of the Xuande emperor, a certain
type of blue and white porcelain from a Chinese
city called Jingdezhen became really popular,
and it remains popular to this day, all over
the world. Other Ming rulers of note include
the Hongzhi Emperor (who was the only Chinese
emperor to have just one wife) and the Wanli
Emperor, who set the stage for the dynasty’s
decline when, part way through his reign,
he refused to perform any of his duties. His
final few years as emperor coincided with the
rise of the later Jin dynasty in the north. They
were led by Nurhaci, who had managed to re-unite
the Jurchen tribes—with the aim of conquering
China like the earlier Jin dynasty had done.
Nurhaci was followed by his son Hong
Taiji, who conquered Inner Mongolia,
putting an end to the NorthernYuan dynasty. Around
the same time, he changed the name of the Jurchen
people to the Manchu people—which is where the
word Manchuria comes from. He also changed the
name of the Jin dynasty to the Qing Dynasty,
because the Chinese letter for Qing contains
the water radical; whereas the letter for Ming
contains the fire radical. Water puts out fire,
so, in other words, he was saying: the
Qing are about to extinguish the Ming.
And he was right because just after he
died, his half-brother Dorgon (serving as
regent for Hong Tai-ji’s son Shunzhi) did
exactly that, capturing Beijing in 1644.
Now, when Beijing fell, a cousin of the last
Ming emperor fled south and from there declared
himself to be the true emperor. He was followed
in quick succession by three other members of the
Ming dynasty (together they are known as the
“Southern Ming” dynasty). In 1662 though, the
Qing conquered the Southern Ming as well, forcing
the final Ming loyalists to flee to Taiwan, where
they took over the island from the Dutch and set
up the Kingdom of Tungning. However, that kingdom
only lasted about 20 years and eventually they
surrendered to the [ching] Qing as well, in 1681.
By this point, the Kangxi emperor was on the
throne. He ended up being the longest-reigning
Chinese emperor of all-time, at 61 years, and
during his reign China once again became stable
and prosperous. He was followed by his son,
and then by his grandson, the Qianlong emperor,
who also had a really long reign. In fact, he
would have beat the Kangxi emperor’s record but
opted to retire after 60 years, out of
respect for his grandfather. During his reign,
China reached its greatest extent,
as you can see from this map here.
During the 19th century however, the Qing
Empire started to decline, especially after
losing the two Opium Wars against the United
Kingdom, which led to the creation of Hong
Kong as a British colony. At the same time
as the Second Opium War, China was also in
the middle of an internal conflict, known as the
Taiping Rebellion. It started when this man—Hong
Xiuquan—claimed to be the younger brother of, wait
for it, Jesus. Hong Xiuquan managed to set up the
Taiping Heavenly Kingdom, centered at Nanjing,
which lasted for about 14 years. In the end,
the Qing armies were able to quash the
rebellion but at a great cost to human life.
Estimates put the death count at around 20-30
million, which is more than that of World War I.
Now, during this tumultuous period, the Xianfeng
emperor died from poor health at age 30,
leading his 5-year old son to become the
Tongzhi emperor. Soon thereafter, his mother,
Empress Cixi staged a coup, placing herself in
the position of regent, so it was actually she
who was in charge at the end of the Taiping
Rebellion. She ended up ruling much longer
than expected though because, just as the Tongzhi
emperor reached adulthood, he died from smallpox,
at which point Cixi made her 3-year old nephew
the Guangxu emperor so that she could continue to
be regent. Even when the Guangxu emperor reached
adulthood, she continued to be the power behind
the throne and therefore ended up serving as
the de facto ruler of China for a total of 47
years. Her last political move, while on her
deathbed, was to arrange the assassination of
the Guangxu emperor by way of arsenic poisoning.
Basically, she didn’t want him reversing any of
her policies after her death. As it turned out,
she actually died just one day after her nephew.
With both main members of the imperial family
now dead, her allies followed her wishes and
made her two-year old great-nephew Puyi emperor
so that they could continue to be in control.
But by this point, Imperial China had been
further weakened by wars against France, Japan,
and then eight nations all at once during the
Boxer Rebellion. In 1911, a revolution broke out,
and by February the next year, Puyi was forced
to abdicate, bringing an end to the 4000-year
monarchy of China. At first, China became the
Republic of China but then, in 1949, as I’m sure
you know, it became the communist-led People’s
Republic of China, which is what it is today.
Now, before I go, I do want to address the
question: Who would be emperor of China today,
if, for some reason, China wanted to restore its
monarchy or if the Qing dynasty had never been
deposed? Well, first off, I want to point out
thatPuyi did actually reign as emperor again,
this time as an adult but also as a puppet of
Japan during the years that they controlled
Manchuria, which they called Manchu-kua.
After World War II, he was held as a prisoner,
first in the Soviet Union, and then later in
Communist China, before finally being released
in 1959 to live out his final 8 years as a regular
citizen (although, obviously, he remained under
close watch). Puyi did marry five times but
never had any children so after his death,
his claim to the imperial throne passed, first to
his full-brother [poo-jyeh] Pujie (who had only
daughters) and then to his half-brother Pu-ren,
better known as Jin [yo-juh] Youzhi. Surprisingly,
he lived all the way to 2015, at which
point the claim passed to his son,
Jin [yoo-jahng] Yuzhang. So it is this man
here who would be emperor of China today.
Okay, so that was a look at the family
tree of Chinese emperors. Once again,
if you want to get a copy of this
chart as a poster, just head over to
UsefulCharts.com or simply click the link
in the description or pinned comment. And
don’t forget to check out our Kickstarter
and pledge for a reward, if you are able.
Thanks for watching.